Finding Aid for the Mason Adams Papers PASC.0215
UCLA Library Special Collections
Mason Adams papers
1937-2006
1977-1993
UCLA Library Special Collections
Adams, Mason
PASC.0215
7.8 Linear Feet (11.5 boxes, 3 cartons, and 1 LP box)
Mason Adams was an actor whose career spanned film, radio, television, and theater. The collection consists of scripts related to Adams' acting career, video and audio tapes, and a small amount of personal material.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mason Adams, 2000.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9944358633606533
Biography
Mason Adams was born Mason Abrams in Brooklyn on February 26, 1919. He received his master's degree from the University of Wisconsin in the early 1940s before returning to New York, where he taught speech for several years at the Neighborhood Playhouse on East 54th Street. It was in the 1940s that he also started his acting career.
He appeared on many major radio programs including Inner Sanctum, Theatre Guild of the Air, and Superman, and he played the title role of Pepper Young in Pepper Young's Family. He has numerous stage credits spanning from his Broadway debut as Joe Rigga in Get Away Old Man (1943) to his last play, The Man Who Had All the Luck (2002). Among his film credits are 9 to 5 (1980), F/X (1986), and Son-In-Law (1993).
Adams made appearances in dozens of television programs, including Matlock (NBC, 1988), Family Matters (ABC, 1991), and The West Wing (NBC 1999). He had a starring role in the short-lived series Knight & Daye (NBC, 1989). Adams is best remembered for his Emmy-nominated role as Charlie Hume on the television series Lou Grant (1977-1982).
He also lent his voice to documentaries and commercials. His distinctive voice became synonymous with the J.M. Smucker Company, which featured him in its commercials for more than 30 years. Adams died on April 28, 2005, in New York City.
Scope and Content
The collection consists largely of film, television, and stage scripts related to the career of actor Mason Adams. However, most of the scripts are for projects that never reached fruition, or that Adams did not appear in. There is only a single script for Adams' Emmy-nominated role on Lou Grant (CBS, 1977-1982), but the entire run of the short-lived sitcom Knight & Daye (NBC, 1989) is present. There is a significant amount of audiovisual material, representing demo reels and appearances by Adams in different media. There is also a small amount of other material, such as clippings, contracts, photographs, and publicity material. Of particular interest might be the detailed notes Adams kept for an acting class he took in 1937.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Series 1. Motion Picture Projects
Series 2. Television and Radio Projects
Series 3. Theater Projects
Series 4. General Files
Series 5. Audiovisual Materials
Folders are in the order determined by the previous archivist.
Actors -- Archives.; Television scripts.; Film scripts.; Adams, Mason--Archives.
- Series 1. Motion Picture Projects
  - Consenting Adults (Buena Vista, 1992)
    - Script by Matthew Chapman, August 20, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Biographical / Historical
      E. G. Marshall played the role Adams was considering.
  - The Empty Mirror (Lions Gate, 1999)
    - Script, November 10, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Final Conflict (20th Century-Fox, 1981)
    - Second draft script by Andrew Birkin, October 1, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - F/X (Orion, 1986)
    - Revised final draft screenplay by Robert T. Megginson and Gregory Fleeman, February 14, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Publicity and stills, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - It's My Turn (Columbia, 1980)
    - Script A Perfect Circle by Eleanor Bergstein, November, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kid Butterfly (unproduced)
    - Screenplay by Doug Jacoby, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 9 to 5 (Twentieth Century-Fox, 1980)
    - Final draft script Nine to Five by Colin Higgins, December 12, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Road Trip (Dreamworks, 2000)
    - Script by Todd Phillips & Scot Armstrong, August 5, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Son in Law (Buena Vista, 1993)
    - Script by Fax Bahr & Adam Small and Shawn Schepps, November 4, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Script by Fax Bahr & Adam Small and Shawn Schepps [lightly annotated], November 4, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Script by Fax Bahr & Adam Small and Shawn Schepps [annotated], December 15, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Publicity and stills, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Shooting schedule, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified
    - Unidentified script, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 2. Television and Radio Projects
  - Adam (NBC, 1983)
    - Shooting script by Allan Leicht, May 17, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American Teacher Awards (Disney)
    - One-minute profiles, December 1, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Appearances (NBC, 1990)
    - Script, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Bliss (unproduced)
    - Pilot script "O Sweet Mystery of Love" by Chip Keyes & Doug Keyes, February 23, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CBS Afternoon Playhouse (CBS, 1978-1983)
    - Script "Secret Agent Boy" by John Francis Whelpley, September 13, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Civil Wars (ABC, 1991-1993)
    - Script "Chute First, Ask Questions Later" by George Malko, January 17, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Class of '96 (Fox, 1993)
    - Script "Episode #1" by John Romano, July 6, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Cocaine: One Man's Seduction (NBC, 1983)
    - Script Cocaine: Another Man's Poison by Barry Schneider, from an original story by David Goldsmith and Barry Schneider, August 27, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Code Name: Foxfire (NBC, 1985)
    - Teleplay "Quicksilver: Slay It Again, Sam" by Richard Chapman and Bill Dial from a story by Joel Schumacher, Bill Dial, and Richard Chapman, October 29, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Diagnosis: Murder (CBS, 1993-2001)
    - Script pages "Open and Shut" by Jacquelyn Blain, July 8, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Robert Stack played the role Adams was considering.
  - Enemy (unproduced)
    - Script by David S. Goyer, based on the Dark Horse Comics character, January 12, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Every Wednesday (unproduced)
    - Script by Clyde Ware and Gloria Gonzalez, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Exit Elves (unproduced)
    - Second draft script "Intermission" by Nancy Miller, January 5, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Family Matters (ABC, 1989-1997; CBS, 1997-1998)
    - Shooting script "Citizen's Court" by Regina Stewart Larsen [annotated], August 21, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Fantastic World Of D.C. Collins (NBC, 1984)
    - Second draft script by Martin Cohan and Phil Margo, May 2, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - For the People (unproduced)
    - Script by Janice Hendler and Larry Brody and Jack Guss, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Goodnight, Beantown (CBS, 1983-1984)
    - Script "First Episode" by A. J. Carothers, December 10, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Great Defender (Fox, 1995)
    - First draft script by Frank Renzulli and George Schenck & Frank Cardea, December 3, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Knight & Daye (NBC, 1989)
    Organization and Arrangement
    Scripts are listed in order of broadcast.
    - Shooting draft script "Sugar Mama" by Kevin Kelton, April 12, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Shooting draft script "New York! New York? " by Bob Pekurny, April 19, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Shooting draft script "Still Motile After All These Years", May 1, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Shooting draft script "Stalk Radio" by Art Everett, May 10, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Shooting draft script "Good-bye Mr. Scrimshaw" by Lowell Ganz & Babaloo Mandel, May 17, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Shooting draft script "The Last Honest Man In America" by Barry Rubinowitz, April 5, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Law and Order (NBC, 1990-2010)
    - Script pages, February 10, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lifestories (NBC, 1990)
    - Script "Life & Death: Colon Cancer" [annotated], 1990 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Biography/History
      Broadcast as "Don Chapin," with Robert Prosky playing the role Adams had considered.
  - Lou Grant (CBS, 1977-1982)
    - Script "Execution" by April Smith [cover inscribed by cast], September 15, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Matlock (NBC, 1986-1992; ABC, 1992-1995)
    - First draft script "The Heiress" by Diana Kopald Marcus, February 24, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Metropolitan Hospital (unproduced)
    - First draft script by Al Aidekman & Rob Dames & Bob Farrelly & Lloyd Garver & Brian Levant & Jeffrey Pohn & Leonard Rips & Bennett Yellin, February 11, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Morningstar/Eveningstar (CBS, 1986)
    - Revised final draft script "A Rose For Alice" by Paul W. Cooper, February 4, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Publicity, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Murder Can Hurt You! (ABC, 1980)
    - Final shooting script by Ron Friedman and Ben Joelson and Art Baer, February 27, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pepper Young's Family (NBC Radio, 1932-1959)
    - Clippings, 1956-1958 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Rage of Angels: The Story Continues (NBC, 1986)
    - Script by Robert L. Joseph, February, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Script pages by Robert L. Joseph, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Raising Caines (NBC, 1995)
    - Third draft script by Bob Brush, January 3, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rise and Shine (unproduced)
    - Revised second draft script by Josh Brand & John Falsey, March 3, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rockenwagner (unproduced)
    - Second draft script by Charles H. Eglee and Channing Gibson, November 27, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Screenplay (BBC, 1986-1993) [UK]
    - Script "Buying a Landslide" by David Edgar, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - There Goes The Neighborhood (unproduced)
    - First draft pilot script, March 16, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - This Is The Life (Syndicated, 1952-1988)
    - Script "In Search of Morgan Avery" by Richard Wendley, April 4, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tomorrow's Child (ABC, 1982)
    - Revised script Genesis by Jerry McNeely, February 9, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Top of the Hill (CBS, 1989)
    - Script The Lame Duck by Stephen J. Cannell, December 23, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Valdez (unproduced)
    - Script "Pilot" by Jeff Valdez and Ed Decter & John J. Strauss, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Voiceovers
    - Scripts and contracts, 1992-2004 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Contains material on a variety of television, radio, and corporate narrations; includes material for Smucker's, the American Parkinson Disease Association, and Wyse Advertising, among others.
  - The West Wing (NBC, 1999-2006)
    - Script pages for episodes 7-10; schedules, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - When In Rome (unproduced)
    - Revised second draft script by Kimberly Hill, February 10, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Where are My Children? (ABC, 1994)
    - Revised script by Michael Zagor, March 8, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Whip Valentine (unproduced)
    - Revised second draft script by Tony Blake & Paul Jackson, March 7, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Wilk, Max shows
    - Treatments, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Who Is Julia (CBS, 1986)
    - Final draft script by James S. Sadwith, based on the novel by Barbara S. Harris, May 19, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Final draft script by James S. Sadwith, based on the novel by Barbara S. Harris [annotated], May 19, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series 3. Theater Projects
  - Adlai, Alone
    - Script by Herbert Mitgang, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Appearances Are Deceiving
    - Script by Thomas Bernhard, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Are You Sure?
    - Script by Sam Bobrick, January 12, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Baby On Board
    - Script by Peter Stone, March 16, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Co-op Chronicles
    - Script and contract, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Script by Charles Grodin, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Script pages, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Diplomacy
    - Script by Chuck Workman, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Downside
    - Script by Richard Dresser, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - EEN
    - Script by Thomas Whipple Hammond, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Few Stout Individuals
    - Script by John Guare [autographed by Guare], 2002 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The Japanese Foreign Trade Minister
    - Script by Murray Schisgal, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Jayhawker
    - Script pages by Sinclair Lewis and Lloyd Lewis, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - The Man Who Had All the Luck (Roundabout Theatre Company, 2002)
    Also played at the Williamstown (MA) Theatre Festival in 2001.
    - Research guide, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Script material and program, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and contact lists, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Includes handwritten letter from Chris O'Donnell.
    - Clippings, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mortal Acts
    - Script by Tom Huey, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Mountain (White Barn Theatre [Westport, CT], 1988)
    - Scripts by Douglas Scott, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - My Father's Song
    - Script by Devon Amber, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - My World and Welcome to It
    - Script material, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Outrage!
    - Script by Henry Denker, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Pete and Jenny
    - Script by Hazel Chilstrom, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Rose Quartet (Circle Repertory Company, 1991)
    - Publicity and correspondence, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - The Sum of Us
    - Script by David Stevens, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Time of Your Life (Mirror Repertory Company, 1986)
    - Notes and contact sheets, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Time Steps
    - Script by Gus Kaikkonen, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A Trip to Bountiful
    - Script by Horton Foote [autographed by Foote], 2005 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - The Value of Names
    - Script, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Waiting in the Wings
    - Script by Noel Coward, revisited by Jeremy Sams, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified
    - Unidentified script, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified script from Jonathan Bernstein, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Series 4. General Files
  - Abrams, Morris, 1982-1990 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Acting notes, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Articles and reviews, 1957-1991 (Box 11, Folder 5-7)
  - Biographical information, circa 1957-2005 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Biographical notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Books, 1945-1996 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    The Best Plays of 1943-1944 edited by Burns Mantle (New York: Dodd, Mead and Company, 1945); Lou Grant by Douglass K. Daniel (Syracuse: Syracuse University Press, 1996).
  - Clippings, 1975-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Contracts, 1986-1999 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Head shots, circa 1937-circa 2000 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Adams, circa 1937-2003 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Adams, 1980-2004 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Includes note from Harold Prince.
  - Membership, 1993-2001 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Obituaries of Mason Adams, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Pension, 1990-1998 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Periodical - Columbus Monthly, December, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Periodical - Manhattan, Inc., November, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Playbills and programs, 1984-2002 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
  - Sheet music, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, circa 1977-2002 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Stills, circa 1977-2001 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Stills, circa 1937-1978 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - University of Wisconsin - diploma and certificates, 1939-1941 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "Winning Orations of the Northern Oratorical League" - pamphlet, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Series 5. Audiovisual material
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this series will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - VHS tapes, 1983-2006 (Box 13)
    Thirty-three cassettes, mostly with various works featuring Adams.
  - Video cassettes, 1988-1997 (Box 14)
    Scope and Content
    Twenty-six VHS cassettes and one Beta cassette of demo reels, theatrical performances, and unknown material.
  - Audio and video tapes, 1985-1999 (Box 15)
    Video tapes of demo reels and unknown material; audio tapes of commercials, books on tape, and unknown material.
  - Phonograph records, 1983 (Box 16)
    Five 2-LP sets of "A True Life Story - Soap Opera."